SANDEEP AGRAWAL

Lawrence, NJ 08648 | (240) 394-2418 | sandeepagrawal2418@gmail.com

Professional Summary

Over 7 years of experience in Android application development and digital strategies. Vast experience partnering with internal and external stakeholders to discover, builds, improve and expand the user experience. Consistently recognized for outstanding contributions and solid reputation for resolving complex issues. Years of successful experience consulting on multifaceted projects and facilitating positive relationships with a wide range of clients, colleagues, and key business partners. Commended for organization, efficiency, priority management, and communication skills. Proven history of creating cutting edge interface designs and information architectures for websites and mobile applications through a user-centered design process by constructing screen flows, prototypes, and wireframes.

Skills

- Bug Resolution
- Android Development
- Retrofitting
- Debugging
- Software Development
- Java

- Mobile App Creation
- Data Structures and Algorithms
- Object-oriented programming
- Coding guidelines
- Testing and maintenance
- Technical Analysis

Work History

Lead Android Developer

04/2019 to Current

Bank Of America – Jersey

- Worked on bug fixes to get understanding of the code base.
- Worked on My Financial Picture feature for the Edge, Advisory and Pre-client apps.
- Implemented Sell Shares feature on the Benefits Online application from scratch. Used Single Activity and multiple fragment approach with MVVM design pattern for the entire feature.
- Facilitated communication between service, design and business team to align user requirements and other team members.
- Worked on redesign on Edge, Advisory and Bol app by reusing new design components and creating several new custom components.
- Worked on suppressing several features for international participant for bol app.
- Designed user interfaces that engaged multiple senses and produced immersive experiences.
- Devised documentation for each app, detailing operation aspects, functions, capabilities and features.

- Provided dedicated support and timely issue resolution to clients following successful app launch.
- Maintained comprehensive knowledge of mobile development cycle and addressed challenges arising in each phase.
- Utilized comprehensive knowledge of mobile landscape, emerging technologies and innovations to remain on cutting edge of Android market.
- Managed aspects of Android app lifecycle from research and planning through deployment and post-launch support.
- Tested applications prior to final review to verify issue resolution.
- Experienced working between numerous devices and versions of Android.
- Created analytics framework to support existing Analytics tool and provide mechanism to add any future Analytics tool.
- Providing estimates for new initiatives
- Performing peer code reviews for immediate and related teams

Android Developer 07/2020 to 11/2020

Chick-fil-A - Remote

- App used by Employees and Managers to learn the skills necessary to operate in a retail environment.
- Users can Sign up and login for their existing domain and see the list of courses assigned to them and make progress on their course.
- Users can also see the status of each course.
- Created UI based on client design using architecture components like navigation.
- Used Kotlin as code base for the entire project.
- Used MVVM architecture.
- Implemented services using Retrofit.
- Firebase crashlytics for crash reporting.
- Custom UI components.
- Encrypting and decrypt for user and password.
- Shared preferences for storing User Preferences.
- Web View for loading courses and handled javascript function inside Web View to suppress certain components inside Web View for mobile.
- Coordinated with client to understand the requirements to create most effective solution.
- Created CI/CD pipeline for running automated tests and distribution using Github actions, Docker and Firebase.
- Used Koin for dependency injection.

Senior Android Developer

03/2017 to 04/2019

Redbox – Oak Brook, IL

• Understand existing code and make recommendations on improving the performance of the android

- application.
- Created UI and functional implementation of the loyalty program in the app.
- Make new UI compatible across multiple devices.
- Participated in daily stand-up meetings and involved with Scrum project estimation meeting on bi-weekly basis.
- Worked on integrating Restful APIs into various parts of the app.
- Working with other developers by collaborating code in Git.
- Integrated custom onBoarding screens in the app.
- Worked closely with UX/ UI team and provide recommendations on best practices.
- Integrated Adobe Advertising SDK into the application to handle the analytics for the application.
- Provide functionality demonstration to the product managers and stakeholders during the development phase and after development is completed.
- Increased the performance of the app by refactoring the existing code.
- Implemented various features in the On Demand section of the app like storefront, auto resuming downloads on network reconnect, applying various filters, managing UI based on data from the API.
- Used Jenkins to deploy the debug and release builds.
- Bug fixes during regression and meeting deadlines to deploy on play store.
- Implemented Masterpass Checkout SDK in the physical checkout in the mobile app and tested in both sandbox and release environment.
- Implemented Localytics SDK in the latest Mobile refresh android app.
- Implemented Push Notification using Firebase.
- Integrated Conviva Analytics third party SDK in the application Provided estimates during plan fest for new features.
- Worked on resolving critical defects during MVP release of the mobile refresh app Implemented
 Facebook and Google Sign In Implemented Firebase Analytics, Firebase Remote Config, Firebase
 Dynamic Links, Firebase Performance Implemented Redbox perks feature using Kotlin and MVVM.
- Helped in bringing crash free users from 95% to 98% within 2 sprints.
- Worked with Koin dependency injection library and Kotlin Coroutines.

Android Developer 12/2013 to 12/2016

AudiobooksNow - McLean, VA

- Discussed and documented client requirements, prepared prototype and shared with the Client Manager.
- Worked closely with another mobile app developer, leading other platform development in Agile methodology.
- Designed interface with Design & UX team for better usability and maintained relative nativity (phones & tablets) Developed user-friendly User-Interfaces (UI) using widgets like Menus, Dialogs, Layouts, Buttons, & Edit boxes; created selection widgets like Listview using Array Adapters & Scroll View as per client needs.

- Tested the app across different versions of Android & Android phones to assure quality and performance Participated in daily stand-up meetings and involved with Scrum project estimation meeting on bi-weekly basis.
- Identifying Critical/Crash/Hidden defects in applications using mobile apps and Ability to give suggestions for quick fix by analyzing logs.
- Updated the application using Android Marshmallow 6.0.
- Integrated the application with the AudioBooks Now restful APIs.
- Created AudioBooks Now for all Android supported Phone, Tablet, Nook, Kindle fire devices.
- Created Custom Player to play AudioBooks.
- Implemented mechanism to read DRM AudioBooks.
- Managing user library locally with the help of SQLite database.
- Implemented Bookmark functionality into the player and synchronize with server.
- Integrated Fortumo payment for Nook application.
- Implemented VLC player for streaming AudioBooks and variable speed audio playback.

Education

Bachelor of Science Information Systems

Strayer University - Arlington, VA

Magna cum Laude, GPA: 3.7

Master of Science: Software Development 03/2022

Boston University - Boston, MA